

Nick Lauersdorf

Computational Physicist and Data Scientist

- Alpharetta, GA
- (608) 852-6337
- ## https://www.njlauersdorf.com
- ☑ njlauersdorf@gmail.com

Social Network

ResearchGate Profile



Github Profile

Languages

Python MATLAB C++

HTML

CSS Javascript 0 0 0 0

SQL

Tools

HOOMD-Blue Mathematica Model Development Tableau

Scikit-learn Seaborn

Pytorch Tensorflow

dj Django

Interests

OpenCV

Video Games Comic Collecting Film

Objective

Computational Physicist seeking to apply 9-years of modeling and simulation, data science, and software development experience to a career in industry. Extensive experience developing physics-based models, writing algorithms to statistically analyze big data, and designing intuitive visualizations to share significant findings.

Education

PhD in Materials Science | UNC-Chapel Hill

2019 - 2024

- Graduate business certificate in Innovation, Leadership, & Management
- Fully paid for 3-years of graduate career by winning the Department of Defense (DoD) National Defense Science & Engineering Graduate (NDSEG) Fellowship

B.S. in Physics and Mathematics | UW-Madison

• GPA: 3.60

Experience

Research & Programming

2020 - current

- Computational Physicist | UNC-Chapel Hill • Discovered meta-stable states of phase separation (clustering) for active Brownian particle mixtures via C++ molecular dynamics simulations
 - Determined phase boundary between stable and meta-stable clusters by training logistic regression machine learning model
 - Allowed differentiation of bulk and interface of cluster by writing local translational and orientational order-based clustering algorithm
 - Enabled design of non-equilibrium steady-states by deriving predictive statistical mechanics theory

Data Scientist | BeAM Makerspaces

- Enabled cost-efficient scheduling and targeted marketing by developing Tableau workbooks for statistical analysis of makerspace user demographics
- Improved end-user experience of staff by leading beta testing of analytics software
- Increased monthly first-time users by 15% by designing marketing visualizations
- Led team that created and implemented a campus-wide inventory tracking system and database

Experimental Physicist | UNC-Chapel Hill

- Expanded lab's presence by forming and managing a collaboration network with numerous national labs
- Taught photodetectors to developing scientists by publishing textbook chapter

Assistant Scientist | Pharmaeutical Product Development

• Increased customer satisfaction by writing FDA-regulated reports

Computational Physicist | UW-Madison

2016 - 2018

2018 - 2019

- Enabled accurate prediction of fusion plasma properties by developing a Bayesian statistics model in Python
- Increased efficiency of model by 40% through converting iterations over lists to multi-dimensional tensor mathematics
- Enabled user-friendly design of x-ray detector optics by developing multi-variable optimization routines to maximize signal
- Increased measurement capabilities of scientists by designing x-ray detector that removes undesirable noise from measurements

Teaching & Mentoring

STEM Mentor | Junior Science & Humanities Symposium 2022 - current

• Earned \$8,000 for two mentees' college funds by placing second at nationals with data science research projects

Teaching Assistant | UNC-Chapel Hill

2020 - 2021

- Introduced others to programming by leading lectures on MATLAB and Python
- Designed molecular dynamics models by overseeing research projects

Awards

NDSEG Research Fellowship [\$165,000] | Department of Defense 2021 - 2024First Place Presentation | Triangle Student Research Competition 2021 Theodore Herfurth Scholarship [\$40,000] | UW-Madison 2014 - 2018